This is a Tool-Assisted Speedrun of Final Fantasy 6 (US) in 3:11:33.46 by Keylie and Kadmony
More information on TASVideos.org
Menu #1: Battle Speed 6, Message Speed 1, Cursor Memory, Magic Order 2, Terra on last slot
Terra was placed on last slot because during preemptives/side attacks, the lowest character acts first
We need Terra to earn as much XP as possible so we made Wedge and Vicks escape
We skipped two fights with this detour
This fight is a forced pincer attack
We cannot escape while the Lobo is alive
Terra got level 4
It would be too long to make Wedge and Vicks escape, because we would have to kill the Vomammoth first
Vicks and Wedge got level 2
Getting a preemptive here wouldn't save time
You can get this first fight or not depending on how your emulator fills uninitialised RAM
We need to win this fight for experience
Terra got level 5
Boss: Whelk. Head is 1600 HP, Shell is 50000 HP
We stay in this menu to freeze the enemy ATB         (wait trick)
Using the wait trick and good startup ATB, it is possible to kill Whelk before it goes in its shell
Having no command window opened at the end of a fight saves a bit of time
Renaming characters to one letter saves several minutes overall
We switch to the party containing Mog, as he's the strongest character
We removed the Mithril Pike and the Mithril Shield from Mog, they will be useful later
Because Terra is level 5, Locks joins at level 7
We wait here a few seconds for luck manipulation
This is forced Back attack
As our average level is 6, Edgar joins at level 8
We will fight the next three battles for XP and money
Terra got level 6
Shopping #1: Buy 3 Sprint Shoes and 1 Goggles
Menu #2: Put Message Speed on 2 and equip Terra with a Sprint Shoes
Walking on light green tiles with a dark green corner cannot trigger a random encounter
Thanks to Message Speed 2, we can escape those battles quickly
We swap the weapon and shield to add lag frames, to get a faster preemptive on the next fight
The incoming boss will feature the first Desperation Attack (DA)
When a character with low HP (< 1/8 max HP) attacks an enemy, he has 1 in 16 chance to trigger a DA
DAs are magical unblockable attacks that ignore defense
However, DAs are unlocked about 25 seconds after the beginning of the fight
Boss: Vargas (11600 HP), Ipooh (360 HP)
Locke is targeting with Steal to freeze Vargas ATB
Sabin cutscene is triggered after 720 HP of damage
With a good startup ATB for Sabin and the previous ATB trick, it is possible to cast Pummel before Vargas
Our average level is 7 so Sabin joins at level 9
The time spend here and everywhere with moving NPCs increases a RNG counter
This counter is used amongst other things to determine how many fights will happen on the Lete River
Because we waited for 3 seconds in Figaro, we don't have to wait here to get the minimum number of fights
The Figaro submerge cutscene is where this counter is increasing the fastest
Menu #3: Sabin gets Sprint Shoes, Edgar gets Genji Glove, Config Battle Speed 1
We set Battle Speed 1 here so that Ultros second attack will happen before the DA is unlocked
We have to set Battle Speed 1 for the fight against Leader anyway
We equip the Mithril Shield on Terra so she can survive Ultros Tentacule
The first two fights were mandatory, the next ones are random
Thanks to the random manipulation, we won't have any
We use quick escapes to increase the RNG counter
So we can get criticals earlier
Ultros will always attack Terra, so she will do the DA in this fight
We unequip the Mithril Shield for a later use
We started with Locke scenario because starting with Terra would trigger an extra fight on the river
Also, we need the Elixir from Locke scenario during Sabin scenario
Menu #4: Locke equips the Sprint Shoes
We enter the house to reset the position of the guard
Menu #5: Nothing
By entering and exiting the menu, it is possible to clip through the guard, saving about 3 minutes
There is a Thunder Rod in this cave that can kill instantly the next boss, but it is too long to take
Menu #6: Locke unequips the Sprint Shoes
We paused a few frames on the last dialogue to manipulate the river for Terra scenario
We are supposed to have Celes here, so she's still talking but does not have a name
Boss: TunnelArmr (1300HP)
We used the "Can't run away!!" message to delay the boss attack
Shadow can join the party here, but it is not worth taking him
Mainly because he will slow down all the escapes
Menu #7: Cyan equips Sprint Shoes
We don't have time to cast Retort without a preemptive
The common drop (Black Belt) will be useful very soon
Menu #8: Sabin equips Black Belt, Message Speed 1
It is not possible to escape a single Ghost quickly with a preemptive
Same as single Ghosts, this is the fastest way to escape a single Bomb
Earrings (like Hero Ring) raises by a factor of 5/4 every magical attacks (including DAs!)
If equipped with two Earrings/Hero Ring, it raises by a factor of 3/2 every magical attacks
Three single Bomb fights is really bad luck
We lost about one second for each one of those fights
Boss: GhostTrain (1900 HP)
We could also use a Fenix Down, but the Elixir has a faster animation
We have to wait for a certain time here
We have to wait for about one minute before the boss Rizopas can appear
Boss: Rizopas (775 HP)
The light green no-encounter tiles don't work here
This fight is unescapable :(
We couldn't manipulate a no-drop fight
Shopping #2: Buy a Dried Meat
As opposed to normally, we can manipulate the enemy formation here
We want formations with at least 3 enemies to be able to escape quickly
Sabin equips the Mithril Shield
Because we skipped Celes, she is replaced with Kutan, a Moggle that appeared at the beginning of the game
This is because Celes character slot was previously occupied by Kutan
Kutan cannot equip weapons, armors, relics or Espers
It is possible to disable the trigger of the fights against those guards
By pressing X (menu) followed by Y (party switch), the game will be kept at an "opening menu" state
Guards won't trigger the fight in that state
Menu #9: Battle Speed 6, Sabin replaces Black Belt with Earrings
Boss: Kefka (3000 HP)
The dropped Peace Ring will be useful for money
Solo Sabin will be enough for Zozo
Every extra character in the team makes the escapes longer by about half a second
We deliberately ignore one no-encounter tile so that the next fight will trigger further from the desert
A danger counter increases at each step by a constant depending roughly on the type of field
Triggering the last fight closer to the desert would have updated that constant to the desert-type (high)
In the end, we would have triggered an extra battle on the way
The save/reset here has multiple purposes:
First, it reset all the encounter constants to other values, saving two fights overall
Second, we will have to farm a specific fight later in the game, and this fight will trigger in one step
Third, we will run across Flan in the Magitek factory, because we need to steal something from them
Taking the Hero Ring here
Preemptives here are very rare, we had to do many weird things in battle to manipulate them
Menu #10: Sabin replaces Sprint Shoes with Hero Ring
Boss: Dadaluma (3270 HP)
Moving up the Sprint Shoes so the next menu is faster
Menu #11: Sabin replaces Hero Ring with Sprint Shoes
Taking the RunningShoes saves time here and there, more in total than the 3 seconds to take them
The previous menu could be avoided with a second character, but not worthy because of slower escapes
The major time-saver of this run is by the use of the sketch glitch with Relm's sketch command
This glitch requires us to learn at least 10 specific magics
This is why we will take Stray and Siren here
Stray teaches Muddle and Imp for 20 Magic Points
Siren teaches Sleep and Slow for 15 Magic Points
We need Sabin and Edgar for the Magitek Factory
Menu #12: Locke gets Sprint Shoes and RunningShoes, Edgar gets Earrings and Hero Ring, Locks gets Stray
You can alter the behavior of the rats by going into the menu
Boss: Ultros (2550 HP)
Edgar DA has the fastest animation, so we choose him to kill the boss everytime it is possible
Shopping #3: Sell Peace Ring, buy 2 Warp Stone and 5 Smoke Bomb
Kutan now has the Celes sprite, but is otherwise as useless as before
Boss: Ifrit (3300 HP) and Shiva (3000 HP)
Ifrit is replaced with Shiva after 5 physical attacks
We can escape the fight during that switch, and the game goes on as if we won the fight
We stole a Magicite from a Flan, an item that casts a random Esper (excluding Odin and Raiden)
We let Kutan die on purpose so that escapes are faster
We also stole a Flash (rare steal), that will be very useful during the Minecart escape
Boss: Number 024 (4777 HP)
We need the Rune Edge for money
One DA is not enough for this boss
We will also sell the drop of this boss (Blizzard)
Menu #13: Order the party as Sabin, Locke and Edgar
The formation of the 5 next fights depends on which character is the leader
Having Sabin as the leader will give the fastest fights
Having Edgar at the bottom allows him to cast Flash quickly
Edgar got level 9 and Locke level 8
Sabin got level 10
Boss: Number 128 (3276 HP), Left Blade (700 HP) and RightBlade (400 HP)
We stole the Tempest (rare steal) for money and the Tincture (rare steal) for the endgame
Locke learns Muddle
Boss: Crane (1800 HP) and Crane (2300 HP)
The Smoke Bomb was used to unlock Joker Doom (JD) from Setzer's slot command
Joker Doom is an instant-death attack to all targets, which include some bosses
During a standard play, a Smoke Bomb would not work
The slots of Setzer are rigged, you have to set a hidden counter to one of several values to unlock JD
This counter starts at zero and is increased during several battle animations by a specific value
The Smoke Bomb raises this counter by 16 times the number of characters, in this case 64
But 64 does not unlock the Joker Doom
However, this counter does not increase instantly, but goes by a lot of values between 0 and 64
If we confirm the first reel of the slots when the counter is set as 16, the Joker Doom will be possible
Terra is back in the team, her level was set again to the average level, which is 9
Menu #14: Terra gets Shoat, Locke gets Siren
We make a little detour to the Triangle Island
The Ragnarok Esper morphs an enemy into an item, which ends the fight
Locke learns Sleep
Thanks to the save/reset, we ran across this Intangir (about 1 in 3 chance) after one step
Fighting this Intangir is the fastest way to learn 10 Magic Points, which is needed to learn the required spells
Fighting him now is useful to unlock Terra's Morph command for Thamasa
Terra's Morph command is unlocked after earning at least 8 Magic Points
The other reason to fight the Intangir now is that we will be able to trigger the sketch glitch as soon as Relm joins
By triggering a fight here, the bridges will switch instantly to the other configuration, saving about 3 seconds
The developers disabled L+R to escape the fight, but didn't bother disabling the Smoke Bomb
The Warp Stone is also possible to escape fights, but it is more expensive and slower for a one-character party
Menu #15: We use a Warp Stone
By exiting and entering again, the red guard that would slow us down is gone
To get the Charm Bangle, we would need to talk to many soldiers and fight guards during the banquet
The Charm Bangle is very useful: it halfs the probability of getting a fight
But getting this item costs about 1 minute to take. It is actually not worth it!
So we have 4 minutes to wait
We order items in advance for the shopping and the sketch glitch
Still 3 minutes to wait
Locke got level 9
Menu #16: Terra gets Earrings, Hero Ring and moves to second slot, we use a Warp Stone
The move to second slot was to escape this fight faster
This second save/reset will save 3 fights until the end of Thamasa
Again, this is faster than getting a preemptive
Shopping #4: Sell Rune Edge, Blizzard and Tempest; buy 2 Fire Rods and 3 Ice Rods
We can influence the pattern of Bombs by delaying entering the rooms
Boss: FlameEater (8400 HP)
We use the wait trick to stop the Balloons
Morphed Terra does twice damage of magical attacks
If the fights ends with Terra's Morph gauge not empty, she will keep the Morph ability
We still need Morph, this why we use another wait trick
Terra learns Bio, Locke learns Mute and Slow
For now, we have 8 magics: Locke got Sleep, Slow, Muddle, Imp; Terra got Fire, Cure, Antdot and Bio
Terra needs 4 Magic Points to learn Break and about 2800 XP to learn Drain
We will have to farm two more fights
After learning these magics, Terra will have Break in the 28th position of her magic list, enabling the sketch glitch
Here is how a slow preemptive escape looks like
Terra got level 12 and learned Drain
Terra learns Break
Menu #17: Terra moves to the first slot, Strago gets Phantom and RunningShoes, set Battle Mode on active
Boss: Ultros (22000 HP)
Using the combination Muddle/Phantom, we can set the Clear status on Ultros
Due to a programming bug, the Clear status overwrite the Death protection
Strago DA is different from the other ones, it casts Death on a single target
Thanks to this fast kill, we skipped a 90-seconds cutscene with Relm
Now that we have Relm, we are ready to trigger the sketch glitch
This glitch happens when Relm's Sketch misses and the first character has a specific magic on 28th slot
It also depends on the availability of that spell, which can be manipulated with the Imp spell
This glitch has the main consequence of overwriting part of your inventory
Thanks to this one, we now have Flame Shields
Also, we managed to equip Goggles in Strago's left hand
By putting the Goggles in a specific slot, the sketch glitch overwrote the item properties but not its type
The item was flagged as a weapon, so we could equip it during the fight
Attacking with Goggles leads to a new glitch
If someone attacks with Goggles and another character opens the Magic menu at a precise time
The Magic menu will display the inventory if scrolled up or down
If an item is used in this glitched menu, the character will cast the magic which has the same id as the item
The game treats Blitz, SwdTech, Tools, Desperation Attacks, enemy attacks, etc. as magics
So all these can be cast using the Goggles glitch
The only restriction is that the corresponding item must be usable in battle
For example, using an Antidote will cast Cyan's desperation attack Back Blade
But we can get around the restriction to usable items thanks to the sketch glitch
Boss: Kefka (5001 HP)
Unfortunately, two Flame Shields barely not killed Kefka
Menu #18: Order the party as: Terra, Strago, Relm, Locke
If Relm has a higher level than the enemy, the Sketch will automatically succeed
That's why we used Muddle to make her miss
Thanks to this Sketch glitch, we got Gem Box and we multiplied Black Belts
Menu #19: Strago gets Gem Box and Black Belt, Relm gets Sprint Shoes, Locke gets RunningShoes, Terra gets Sprint Shoes and Gem Box
We first trigger a sketch glitch to make the Black Belt usable
Strago has to equip a buckler to be able to attack with Goggles
The Magic corresponding to Black Belt is Engulf, which targets the enemy by default
That is why we need Muddle to cast Engulf on the party
The Goggles glitch was triggered with the X-Magic command so Terra can cast Engulf twice
To Engulf the remaining two characters, we used the counter-attack
Because the whole party was engulfed, we end up inside the Zone Eater
By taking the exit, we are warped to the World of Ruin!
We need a last sketch glitch to equip Moggle Charms and Goggles on 3 characters
The setup here is longer: 4 Tincture then Imp on Terra
This glitch caused a lot of lag :(
Now Terra, Locke and Strago have one Moogle Charm and one Goggles equiped
Moogle Charm removes all random encounters
The last sketch glitch also corrupted the character sprites, and is causing a 10-seconds freeze
By using a switch party trick, it is possible to pass through a tile without triggering its event
It requires to press X then Y immediately after, then change the leader
Menu #20: Swap Locke and Sabin, Sabin gets Stray
We passed through the tile that triggers the fight against Inferno
Equipping an Esper on Sabin is to unlock his Magic command during battle
Menu #21: Relm gets Ramuh
This time we use the Goggle glitch with the X-Potion item, resulting in casting Bababreath
This spell automatically ejects the target from the battle
We used that time to put the Fire Shield on top of the inventory
Menu #22: Cyan gets Maduin
We used twice the party switch trick to walk the conveyor belt backwards
This skips another boss (Poltergeist)
If we cast Bababreath on Kefka, it would trigger the second tier
If one character is bababreathed, however, the game considered that the fight was not lost
So it triggers the ending sequence
The movie ends now