This is a Tool-Assisted Speedrun created by エディ, kadmony, keylie and pirohiko
The final time is 24:33.26, using 23592 rerecords
This TAS uses the 52 gameover glitch to trigger the ending
This glitch has been documented in a previous submission on tasvideos.org website
In short, after dying 52 times in the world map, the game loads a corrupted value of the event pointer
By manipulated this value, we can execute script code from RAM, and trigger the ending
Message Speed to 1, Cursor to Memory, remove all equipment from Terra
We need Terra to die without loosing much time
The best fight to do that is this Pincer attack
We need one soldier to escape so the other one reaches level 3
This is mandatory for the quick Whelk fight
Terra level 4, Vicks level 2, Wedge level 3
This is a new trick: casting Def. with Terra speeds up the escape by 4 seconds
We need to walk extra steps at some point. Doing it here speeds up the ATB manipulation
Thanks to Battle Speed is 3, Whelk shell will take two turns before hiding
This allows Whelk head to fight twice
We need Terra to die in this fight, but she needs to do two attacks before being killed
We also must manipulate each attack to be of high damage in the value range
We setup the inventory for later
slot 2: Leather Hat, slot 4: Buckler, slots 0/1/3: empty
Terra is renamed "TE" to manipulate a savefile checksum later
We are going to escape Narshe through this door
There is currently a NPC blocking this door, but we will use the first savefile to overwrite it
We first need to reach the save point
It is crucial to trigger a fight next to the save point (hence the extra steps)
Slot 3 is our backup, slot 2 is the one we will work on
First, we overwrite the savefile until NPC addresses, and reset
We now have the Terra/Vicks/Wedge party, but we want the solo Terra party
So we overwrite the party addresses in slot 2 with the solo Terra party
At last, we need a dead Terra
So we load the first slot, and we overwrite the Terra status addresses
Thanks to the Terra renaming, the checksum of the second savefile is correct!
Because the party is dead, we must not have a fight in this area
This is why we saved just after a fight
Our inventory is nearly complete, we only need the Mithril Pike
In the previous TAS we got it from Mog
Fortunately, we can buy it in Narshe!
We also need the hex value of our money to end with C4
The easiest value to reach is 452 (1C4)
We just have to buy 4 Mithril Pike and sell 1 Sleeping Bag
We are almost ready, we need to save outside just before a fight
And inputting the code to trigger the ending using menu colors
Thanks to Eddie, there is a faster way to start the 52 gameovers
If you die against the monster-in-a-box fight, it will count as 3 fights
And now starts the remaining fights...
Having a dead party saves about 2 minutes
You can skip to 24min for the last fights